welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
okay all right
everybody knows the drill here there's a
couple quick things I want to share so a
few of us are trying to build a habit of
writing and so there's an open zoom room
for writers every weekday at 6:30 I'll
drop this in the chat at the end of the
slide it's basically one hour we just
come to a zoom room write our writing
intentions in the chat and then write
for an hour together and that's been
going really great this week I think we
had around six or seven people on a
daily basis this week another thing is
there's a metagame slack channel and if
you haven't joined that already I highly
recommend you do and I'll also drop that
link in the chat but I just want to
quickly get into tonight's theme which
is this concept of hard versus soft
discipline and I think this is an
important idea that will really help to
keep at the back of your mind whenever
you're doing any kind of accountability
with anybody in the in the coming weeks
so first it helps to understand what we
really mean by self-discipline to begin
with and it's really this idea of
aligning yourself with what you want to
do so that to pursue what you think is
right despite the temptations to abandon
that and it goes to the root word of
this year which means to learn and
deceptively na which means instruction
and training so self discipline in a way
is like self teaching self learning to
do what you think is right and you can
tell this is quite similar to the idea
of sovereignty with tweeting
initially open with but I want to add a
couple flavors to it and these are just
I guess like my words for it
and there isn't any scientific basis to
what I'm saying but I think these are
useful concepts in my experience there's
two types of discipline and one of them
is hard discipline which is what most
people think of when they think of self
discipline which is when you reach this
alignment of your actions with your
better judgment through
willpower effort or social pressure so
you can think of traditional
accountability groups doing a version of
this you can think of whenever you try
to get yourself to do something that is
hard like wake up in the morning you're
using heart discipline and for most
people this is where the concept of
discipline starts and ends I want to
propose to you that there's another idea
which we'll call soft discipline which
is when you're aligning your actions
with your better judgment through better
understanding now this is obviously a
little bit vague err so I think it helps
to think of an example let's say you're
trying to quit smoking you can throw
away all your cigarettes you can try to
practice willpower for a 30-day period
you can get your friends to hold you
accountable or I actually heard this one
example where somebody made some sort of
commitment contract where if they had
another cigarette they would donate a
few thousand dollars to the KKK or
something like that some undesirable
outcome was related to the activity and
that would be a hard discipline approach
but there's been many cases of people
quitting smoking through a soft
discipline approach where all of a
sudden they have an epiphany that it's
bad for them and they stop maybe
somebody in their family got lung cancer
maybe they had a some sort of
psychedelic episode where they're you
know eyes kind of opened up to how
destructive this whole smoking thing is
in fact there's a study on this the most
effective smoking cessation study was a
study where they gave a bunch of
participants who were chronic smokers
reasonably high dose of psilocybin and
at the end of the study over 80% of them
had quit smoking in that one-time event
and they followed up with them I think a
year after and it had still maintained a
smoke-free life so clearly there are
other ways let's say and I'm gonna use a
soft discipline model to refer to those
ways where you have an epiphany or some
sort of change in understanding or your
felt sensor relationship with the
difficult behavior changes
this is related to this other concept
that goes back to the Greeks called
akrasia which is acting against your
better judgment through weakness of the
will and for some this is a useful
concept the idea that there are certain
things that you want to do that are just
hard to do and so you don't have enough
will to actually do those things and so
- to the extent that you don't do them
you're a kradic but then some people say
a creator doesn't actually exist and
really what's happening is you just
never wanted to do the thing to begin
with you didn't really have the better
judgment willpower
didn't even factor into it so these
questions may seem significant you may
wonder what what type of discipline is
better in what situation does a crazy
even exist and actually there's people
who have a lot of debates about this
stuff and what I'd say to all of this is
that it doesn't really matter because
we're playing the meta game here and
we're evaluating the quality of these
models based on their utility and we are
not maintaining any kind of commitment
to any one approach we are not going to
judge hard discipline we're not going to
judge soft discipline we're not going to
judge the concept of a Croatia it's
basically the goal is to operate from a
position of non-judgmental
a non-judgmental perspective where
you're able to use wisdom to decide
which of these models is most suitable
for what you're trying to do in the
moment and I want to flag this here
because obviously this is kind of a
broader topic but as we continue to do
various forms of accountability it's
important to always step out of whatever
frame you're in step out of even the
accountability model and just take a
meta frame and look at what is actually
the most useful for what we're trying to
do so with that I want to talk about how
this stuff relates to cruise relates to
masterminds traditionally accountability
groups use hard discipline as we
described earlier and I think there's a
lot of stuff out there about this you
know you create the commitment contracts
the prototype that we presented last
week and that some of you have started
to practice this week explicitly at
least has more of a heart discipline
approach where you have a bunch of your
commitments being tracked and you have
people that are checking in with you but
what I want to introduce is this idea
that good cruise the best cruise
actually helped with the soft discipline
piece and there's at least two ways
through which they do this one of them
is the cruise themselves so these groups
of three people in this case but maybe
maybe up to eight people they start to
develop implicit or explicit standards
and values like you can actually write
down what your standards and values are
and that those those values start to
subtly shift the values of the people
within that group so and you know they
talk about how their studies that show
that people are roughly as healthy as
the friends that they spend the most
time with there's a famous self-help
quote that your the average of the five
people you spend the most time with
these things happen through self
discipline you're not looking at your
friends and then trying to force
yourself to be more like them that's not
happening it's more so that over the
long term the standards start to shift
your behavior and then the other point
which I think is a is really the
interesting one and the one that I want
to highlight is that cruise can help by
shining the light of truth on everyone's
blind spots so if we go back to the idea
that soft discipline is about getting a
better understanding of a situation so
take the smoking case you you actually
understand the full experience of what
it means to be a smoker right when you
when you develop that kind of
understanding of how it affects you how
how it's affecting your lungs and all
that information becomes more available
to you you're bringing the truth about
the situation to a higher level of
salience and that's what's making it
easier to overcome the smoking habit and
my hypothesis with those psilocybin
studies is that's what psilocybin does
it kind of changes the salience
landscape and all of a sudden smoking
means something else now I'm not
suggesting everybody have these you know
epiphanies moments or takes
dellux but what I am saying is that
crews can do that exact same thing over
the long term as long as everyone in the
crew has a commitment to telling the
truth to one another and to shining
light on everybody else's blind spots so
that's pretty much it that's the main
takeaway from this and I'll stop there
so that we can have some discussion and
to begin I just like to hear openly from
everybody what does everybody think
about that what does this idea seem
useful do you have examples of hard
discipline and soft discipline in your
own lives I just love to hear from
anyone